本影音版权属其出版、发行方，字幕制作仅供学术交流之用 请于下载后24小时内删除，并不得有公开传播或作商业盈利之行为 若有违法等相关行为，诸神字幕组恕不承担任何法律或连带责任。
翻译 koki  放 晴  La Fatalité
I realized it too late.
遅すぎた　気づくのが…
压制 暗之亚瑟王  校对 凉YAN Lucifer 时间 Lucifer
No. There is still time.
否　まだ間に合う
You want to see the true
Heaven, do you not?
真の天国を見たくはないかね？
Who are you?
貴様は…
I abandoned my human name long ago.
人の名はとうに捨てた
The believers call me...
信徒たちは私をこう呼ぶ--「楽園管理者」と
The Overseer of Paradise.
止まる者　愚かなりし
The one who stops is foolish
はらりひらり指に触れた黒い翼の　一片
A piece of black wing gently touches fingers
诸
神字幕组
君が一つの　物語なら
If you were a story
まだいくらでも　掛け替えられる
You could still rewrite it all you want
血のインクは乾かない
The ink of blood doesn't dry up
誰も知らない　本との僕ら
No one knows the real us
荒れた世界　枯れるのは
What changes the chaotic world
追い求めたのは　ちっぽけな幸福なんかじゃない
What we pursued isn't
Small happiness
戦え　轟く　音を合図に
Fight with a rumbling heartbeat as a sign
意のまま　進めば
What awaits you is infinite if you
move forward as you wish
行く先　果てない
抗え　のたうち
Fight off no matter how many
times you get defeated
幾度と　汚れと
膝を纏った傷跡に夢を
Engrave your dream onto the scar you bear
埋もれそうな今日の記憶繋げるために　明日へ
In order to connect today's memory that's
on the verge of being buried to tomorrow
Episode 9
A True Man, a Battlefield, and My World
第9话 真人
与
战场
和
我的世界
Nope.
駄目だな
I know that there's knowledge
contained in the Nonentity Entrails,
仮想臓腑の中に知識が詰まっているのは分かる
but that's all.
だがそれだけだ
The same conclusion the
Magic Bureau reached, huh?
魔道庁の見解どおりか
Enlike, you may be able to
take over Zatoh's body,
エンリケ君
君はザトウの体を乗っ取ることはできても
but you won't be able to take
over his magic rights.
やつの魔法権利までは乗っ取れない
I'd wager that Zatoh's
personal magic right
食った「本」の力を使うのも
is the ability to use the powers
of the Books he eats.
恐らくザトウ個人の魔法権利なんだろう
You cannot eat Books and you
cannot use cloth or water-
事実　今の君は「本」を食う事も
布や水弾も…
You love the sound of your
own voice, Mattalast.
よく喋る男だな　マットアラスト
Anyway, what do you plan
to do with me?
で　俺をどうするつもりだ？
Nothing.
別に　このバントーラで好きに過ごすといい
Take your time. Enjoy Bantorra.
Read some Books. Go into town
and find a girl to fool around with.
「本」を読むなり
街に繰り出して好みの女の子を侍らすなり
なんなら御供するぜ
Heck, if you want, I'll join you.
Relax. We've already tried to kill each
other once. We're brothers now.
気にするな
一度は親しく殺し合った仲じゃないか
Matt? It's Milepoc.
マットさん　ミレポックです
Do you have a minute?
今　宜しいですか？
Sure, I was just getting sick of
talking to a stubborn young man.
頑なな少年の相手にも少し飽きたところだ
A graceful lady like yourself
is a nice change of pace.
麗しきレディーなら大歓迎
From what we learned
from Enlike's statement,
エンリケの証言に基づき
True Man Ganbanzel's estate was
spotted in the Ismo Republic.
「真人」ガンバンゼルの屋敷をイスモ国内で発見しましたが
However, it's completely abandoned,
and he's nowhere to be found.
すでに人影はなく　足取りは掴めていません
I see. Good work.
そうかよ　ご苦労
Time sure flies.
早いものね
It's been a week since Enlike
came to this island.
エンリケさんがこの島に来てもう一週間
Befriending a member of the Church is huge.
教団の一員を見方にできたのは大きいわ
I wonder if the Acting Director anticipated
all this happening from the start.
代行はこれを見越して単独行動してたのかしら
Who knows.
さてね
Do you think she'll make
him an Armed Librarian?
彼を武装司書にする気だと思う？
I couldn't say.
どうだろう？
Besides, Enlike doesn't seem
too interested himself.
それにエンリケ本人にその気がないしな
You impress me, Enlike.
いい目になったわね　エンリケ君
You're an entirely new person compared
to when we met in town.
前に街で会ったときとは別人
Say, wanna battle to the death right now?
ね　今からでもあたしと殺し合わない？
We can destroy this place
without anyone caring.
ここならあばれ放題よ
You may have a reason to fight,
あんたに戦う理由があっても　今の俺にはない
but I don't.
Shucks.
あら？
I came here to atone for my sins.
ここへ来たのは　罪を償うためだ
I owe her.
こいつには　一応借りがある
You're so cruel to me.
つれないのねえ
失恋しちゃった
My heart is broken.
Change your mind someday,
will ya? I'll be waiting.
まぁいいわ　いつか振り向いてね
待ってるから
A former Church member becoming
an Armed Librarian?
元教団員が武装司書
You shouldn't even joke about that.
冗談にしてもまったく質が悪い
You're back now, Feekiee?
フィーキさん　お戻りだったの？
How did things go on the island?
例の島　どうだった？
Not great.
然したる収穫はない
ハイザの「本」だけはなんとか回収できたが
But I did manage to recover Hiza's Book.
I see.
そうか
True Man Ganbanzel is missing.
「真人」ガンバンゼルは行方知らず
And just as with the incident involving Cigal,
シガルの事件と同じく　教団の手がかりもろくに掴めない
we're having trouble finding
clues about the Church.
In any case, it's only a matter of time
まぁ　抛っておいてもいずれ
before that spy shows his true colors.
あのスパイが尻尾を出すだろうかね
うん　君もそう考えてるのか？
You think so, too?
Of course.
当然だろう
No matter how you slice it, he's still
the man who attacked the Library.
なにしろ奴は　仮にも一度この図書館を襲撃した男だ
I find it hard to believe that he'd
sever all ties with the Church.
とても神溺教団と切れているとは思えん
Ow-ow...
いたた…
They told me that you can
only use thunder magic now.
雷以外の魔法はもう使えないって聞きましたけど
My hyper-regeneration
is separate from that.
超回復は別だ
この力は　カヤスが俺のために残してくれたのかもしれん
I think Kayas may have left this
power behind for me.
Okay then, round two.
では改めて　きっちり叩きのめしてあげます
This time, you'll be the one knocked down.
今度こそ
Sounds like fun. Bring it on.
面白い　やってみろ
Oh! You just smiled, Enlike.
あっ　エンリケさん　今笑いましたね
I did not.
笑ってない
笑いました
You did!
I did not.
笑ってない
All right, 1000 kiluwes
on the one who smiled.
うーん　にやけたほうに千キルエですかねぇ
I'll bet 2000 kiluwes, then.
じゃぁ　あたし二千キルエ
Guys... Why are you...
皆さん　どうして…
Oh, this guy said he wanted to
spar with the "Book Eater".
やーはぁ　どうしてもこちらの方が
噂の「本喰い」さんと手合わせしたいってんで
I'm Ruweek, a 2nd-rank Armed Librarian.
二級武装司書のルイークだ
W-Wait. He's not a Book Eater anymore...
あ、あのう　この人はもう「本喰い」とかじゃなくて…
Duh, we know that.
知ってるよ　こんなの
That being said...
でもだからって
So you don't trust me.
信用できんというわけか
He's bright. I love men like that.
話の早い男　好きよ
Guys, let's not go through with this.
なぁ　止さないか　もし代行に知れたら
If the Acting Director found out...
Shut up, Gamo.
黙ってろ　ガモ
I don't care what the top brass has to say.
It doesn't sit right with me.
たとえ上がどうだろうと　納得いかない
Gilda, the regular librarian
this jerk killed,
こいつに殺された一般司書のギルダは　俺の同郷だったんだ
was from my hometown!
I'm in pain.
いた…
I told you so.
いわんこっちゃない
Damn it...
畜生
けどすごい雷だったんすねぇ
But wow, he sure can use thunder...
戦闘力だけだったらあいつ　一級武装司書並みじゃないすか
Purely in terms of combat prowess,
don't you think he's on par with
the 1st-rank Armed Librarians?
He is a monster.
それ　怪物だし
Yeah. What is the Acting Director thinking,
それにしても　あんなの泳がしとくなんて
letting him wander free like that?
代行も一体なに考えてるのか
Don't be worried.
心配ないですよ
Ruweek, despite his tough
looks, is a good guy.
ルイーク先輩　あー見えてもいい人ですから
I'm sure he'll come around.
きっと分かってくれます
See you again tomorrow.
それじゃ　また明日
Yeah.
あっ
出て来い　ガンバンゼル
Show yourself, Ganbanzel.
Ganbanzel? Where?
ガンバンゼル？
どこにいるの？
Are you going to haunt me forever?
いつまで俺に付き纏うつもりだ
Humans...
人間 それはこの世のすべての幸せを得る権利のあるもの
Beings with the right to gain all the
happiness this world may offer.
Where's your body located?
貴様の本体はどこだ？
Wounded humans are to be saved.
傷ついた人間は助けねばならぬ
Suffering humans are to be rescued.
苦しむ人間は救わねばならぬ
Forsaken humans are to be loved.
孤独な人間は愛されねばならぬ
What says a monster about this?
では　怪物にとってはどうか？
The exact opposite.
答えは否
Wounded humans are to be killed.
傷ついた人間は殺めねばならぬ
Suffering humans are to be trampled.
苦しむ人間は踏み躙らねばならぬ
孤独な人間は食らわねばならぬ
Forsaken humans are to be devoured.
Enlike, return to me.
エンリケよ　帰れ　我が元へ
You're a true monster. You defeated Zatoh!
ザトウを倒したお前こそ真の「怪物」
Serve my desires. Serve my wishes!
我が野望　我が望み
Stay away from me!
寄るな
My monster... Just you wait...
怪物よ　待っておれ
You will come to me.
必ずこの手に…
I'm impressed.
見上げたものだ
Sending your spirit after him over and over,
at the expense of shortening your own life...
己の命を削ってまで
魂を彼の元へ飛ばし続けるとは
Obsession like that will have Heaven
welcoming you with open arms.
その妄執
天国は君を喜んで　迎え入れるだろう
What's this? You look like
you've seen a ghost.
あらー　そんな怖い顔して
What did you see?
一体何が見えるのかしら
Why?
なぜ　なぜ貴様のような奴が　館長代行などしている？
Hmm?
How can a woman like you
be the Acting Director?
Her smile is practically that of...
あの笑顔は　まるで…
A monster?
怪物だって？
Thank you for your kind words.
お褒めいただけありがとう
In return, I shall tell you a neat fact.
お礼にひとつだけ　いいこと教えてあげる
What I want
あたしはね
is a battle to the death with someone
hellbent on killing me.
あたしを殺したくて殺したくてたまらないていう相手と殺し合いたいの
I see that blood-thirst in
your eyes right now.
今の君　そういう目をしているわ
You're mad!
狂ってる　貴様は
うふん　まーた褒められちゃった
Oh, you're too kind!
Take that Book with you.
その「本」　持っててもいいのよ
It'll give you nice memories
when you're feeling lonely.
寂しくなったらいつでも　思いだしてね
What? Went into town by himself?
え　ひとりで街に下りた？
Enlike did?
エンリケさんがですか？
He'll be fine. We've got
surveillance on him.
大丈夫　監視はつけてあります
Noloty!
ノロティさん
Hamy, do you really want to
fight that boy this badly?
ハミュッ　お前そんなに戦いたいのか？ あの坊やと
Yeah, I do.
まぁーね
I mean, it's not that I'd fight just
anyone simply because they're strong.
でも　強い相手なら誰だっていいわけじゃないのよ
After all, I never expected
much out of Zatoh.
ザトウなんて　端から期待してなかったものねぇ
He was just killing people for fun, right?
あいつはさ　しょせん楽しくて殺してただけでしょう？
Anyone can do that.
あんなのただの小物よ
The strongest of all, Matt,
一番強いのはね　マット
are the people who fight to save others.
他人のために戦うやつ
Those who come at you with
everything they've got
勝ち目があろうとなかろうと　命がけで向かってくるもの
regardless if they stand
a chance of winning...
本当よ
For example, that young person.
たとえば　あの子みたいにね
Anyway, I just want to see
what he's made of.
のっ　ここはお手並み拝見といこうじゃない
Don't disappoint me, Ganbanzel.
ガンバンゼル君に乞うご期待
Monster, return to me.
怪物よ　我が元へ帰れ
Shut up.
Monster, return to me.
黙れ…黙れ…
Shut up.
What's he mumbling to himself about?
なにひとりでぶつくせ言ってるんだ？
Who knows...
さぁー
Noloty!
ノロティ
Enlike!
エンリケさん
あっ　どうかしたんですか？
Is something wrong? You look pale.
顔色悪いですよ
ノロティ
Noloty...
Kill. Kill, monster.
殺せ　殺せ　怪物
Shut up!
黙れ！
You're a monster.
お前は怪物　お前は私のもの
You belong to me.
Enlike-
エンリケさん…
Shut up!
黙れ！
もう俺のことは構うな
Just keep away from me.
It's just that we live in different worlds.
お前と俺では　しょせん生きる世界が違う
Noloty!
ノロティ
Are you okay, Noloty?
ノロティ　大丈夫？
That jerk!
あの野郎
Hold on!
待ってください
But...
でも…
He's trying to do something very important.
あの人　なにか大事な事をしようとしてるみたいなんです
Uh...
うん…
It's fine.
まぁ　いいだろう
As long as he's on this island,
この島にいる限り
he won't be able to escape the
Acting Director's sensory threads.
代行の触覚糸からは逃れられっこないしなぁ
That's the Acting Director's
transmission capsule.
代行の通信弾だ
"Right on!"
ピンポン ノロティの言うとおり
"Listen to Noloty..."
"...and don't do anything stupid."
野暮はしちゃ駄目よね
Monster, return to me.
怪物よ　我が元へ帰れ
Fine. I'll do as you like.
分かった　貴様の望みどおりにしてやろう
He agreed?
動いたか？
Yes.
あー
Then I shall send you, man of truth.
では送っていこう　真なる人よ
Years ago, when you had the misfortune to be
in Ronar Dukedom on business,
数年前　商用で折悪しくロナ公国を訪れていた君は
you ended up in the midst
of that pointless war.
あの理不尽な戦乱に巻き込まれた
Move! A-A-A monster is coming!
退け　か、怪物が来る
Hurry!
早くしないと殺されるぞ
Drag him out!
Hurry!
Get on! Move!
He'll be killed!
Let me on, too!
俺も乗せろ
俺も乗せてくれ
Let me on, too!
The invasion of Ronar Dukedom
by the Guinbecs Empire.
海国グインベクスによるロナ公国への侵略戦争
And then the military intervention by the
Armed Librarians, which you witnessed.
そして武装司書による武力介入を目の当たりにした君は
Seeing this awoke you to your true nature,
and you began to thirst for overwhelming power.
己の本性に目覚め　圧倒的な力を渇望するようになった
Are you all dead?
死んだのか？　みんな
I realized it too late.
遅すぎた　気づくのが…
No. There is still time.
否　まだ間に合う
You want to see the true
Heaven, do you not?
真の天国を見たくはないかね？
Do you know what you should do
to experience the joy of living?
生きる喜びを得るにはどうすればよい？
Kill!
殺すことだ
Your opponent dies, and you live.
自分が生き　相手が死ぬ
That's the joy you'll feel.
その幸福を味わうことだ
You realized this on that battlefield.
あの戦場で君は悟った
You set off to create a monster to
destroy everything in your stead.
己に代わってすべてを滅ぼす怪物
That pure desire made you
into a man of truth.
それこそが　君の「真人」たる純粋な望み
Do you regret doing it?
後悔してるかね？
You had to abandon everything in
your life to accomplish this...
そのために人生のすべてを捨てたことを
Old friends...
親しき友を 長年築いた地位を
Status which you had spent
decades building...
Your beloved wife...
愛しき妻を 掛け替えのなき娘を
Your precious daughter...
All of them earthly desires.
すべてそれは　煩悩
All of them detestable!
すべて唾棄すべきもの
For their lives are...
なぜなら　彼らの生など
...all transient in nature.
すべて　仮初め
お帰り　我が愛しき怪物
Welcome back, my beloved monster.
Ganbanzel.
ガンバンゼル
Come, show me your power
which shall obliterate all.
さぁ　見せておくれ
すべてを殺し尽くすお前の力を
I will protect the world, without killing!
私は殺さずに　世界を守って見せます
I...
俺は
You belong to me.
お前は私のもの
No...
違う
You're a monster. This world
has no place for you.
お前は怪物
この世のどこにも居場所などない
No.
違う
Isn't that right, Enlike?
そうだろう　エンリケ
No!
違う
Yes! That's the way, monster!
そうだ　それでよい怪物よ
さぁ
Shut up!
黙れ
Kill everything, just like Hamyuts Meseta does.
全てを殺せ　あのハミュッ=ツメセタのように
Shut up!
黙れ
Kill! Kill for me!
殺せ　殺すのだ
Shut up!
黙れ
Yes, show me your power!
さぁ　見せてくれ　お前の力を
Shut up!
黙れー
How wonderful...
素晴らしい
Death rains from the skies,
just like that day...
死が空から　あのときのように
おお…なんという幸せ
My, such delight.
Achieve thy true desire.
己の真の欲することをなす　それが「真人」の務め
Such is the duty of a True Man.
The Books of those who fulfill their desires
and live their life in happiness
欲望を全うし
幸福に生涯を終えたものの「本」は
shall ascend into Heaven.
天国へと捧げられる
True Man Ganbanzel,
「真人」ガンバルゼルよ
君の幸福が伝わってくるぞ
I can feel your happiness.
I accept your Book.
この「本」　しかともらい受けたぞ
Looks like they didn't make it.
いまだ事至らずって感じねえ
I guess they scored a 65?
65点てとこかな
All that happened while I was gone?
留守中にそんなことが
Did they check whose body it is?
遺体の証拠は？
Did they verify it was Ganbanzel's?
確かにガンバンゼルのものだったんですか？
We don't know.
We have no way to check. Just...
分からないわ　確かめようがないもの
ただ…
As always, it's what the Acting Director said.
例によって　代行の一声さ
The Librarians seem to see Enlike
in a different light now.
死体はどうあれ　司書たちのエンリケさんを見る目は
変わってきてるわ
ミンスが「聖浄眼」で口添えしたのも聞いてるけど
Minth's read on him with his
Sacred Eyes influenced them, too.
What did he say?
なんと？
His dominant trait is stupidity,
相は愚　思考は混沌　望みは消滅
his thoughts are of chaos,
and he wishes for destruction.
A bunch of phonies...
司書らしい振りよ
We're in serious trouble with so
many weaklings in our ranks!
うちの連中はあまちゃんが多くて困る
Where are you going?
どこ行くんですか？
Noloty...
ノロティ
We live in a different worlds.
私とは生きる世界が違う
That's what you said, huh?
そう言いましたよね
Yes. I'm leaving this island.
ああ　俺はこの島を出る
We're the same.
同じなんです
You live in my world, Enlike.
エンリケさんも生きてるんです 私のこの世界に
So,
だから　一緒に守ってください
please protect the world with me.
この世界を
Long, long ago, over 2000
years in the past,
遥か2000年もの昔
mankind spoke softly and were
satisfied with their lots in life.
人々は多くを語らず 足るを知り
It is said they lived together in
the mutual pursuit of happiness.
互いに幸せに満ち溢れて暮らしていたと聞く
It was truly the age of paradise.
それすなわち　楽園時代
But the gods left. The humans, alone,
remained to lament and grieve.
神々が去り
この世には嘆き悲しむ人間たちだけが残された
But they were ignorant to the fact
だが彼らは知らぬ
that Heaven still exists here on Earth!
天国は　未だこの世に留まっていることを
My name is the Overseer of Paradise.
我が名は　「楽園管理者」
I carry this secret with me.
密かにその秘密を受け継ぐもの
Oh, me?
あら　あたしは？
I leave the rest to you.
後は宜しく
Much obliged.
心得た
Happiness.
幸福を
Lost the light
Before closing the sun
If it's a sparkling storm
Jump in before it tempts
The end comes to everyone one day
When the day comes
Aim for the future that begins to move
Even if it's already been written
Search and even acquire the
meaning of getting hurt
In order to be myself
Lovers,
A foolish clown built
愚かな道化が作り出した
Lovers, a Mother,
A foolish clown built
a labyrinth of nothingness.
虚無の迷宮
Take one step in, and you'll encounter
一歩足を踏み入れれば
怪人与母亲和黑蚁之巢
Lovers, a Mother, and the Black Ants' Nest
Take one step in, and you'll encounter
death as dark as night.
そこに待つのは
桎梏の死